Vikram Ramavarapu

Github: Github Link

Linkedin: Vikram Ramavarapu

vikramr2@illinois.edu

vikramr2.github.io

Research Interest: I am interested in learning about and designing algorithms to solve problems in biology. I am especially interested in learning about protein folding, drug discovery, and phylogeny estimation. I am also interested in the application of machine learning to various aspects of clinical practice.

Education

University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign

Aug. 2022 – May 2024

MS. Computer Science: Bioinformatics

Champaign, IL

· Course Work: Bioinformatics, Algorithmic Genomic Biology

University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign

Aug. 2019 – May 2022

BS. Mathematics and Computer Science

Champaign, IL

• **GPA**: 3.79

• Course Work: Adv. Algorithms, Deep Learning, Web Programming, Database Systems, Numerical Analysis, Partial Differential Equations, Graph Theory, Real Analysis

Conference Presentations

Demystifying Digital Home Assistant Devices for Older Adults with and without Disabilities

Kadylak, T., Blocker, K.A, Gowrishankar, S., Malecki, M., Galoso, L., Khamzina, M., Ramavarapu, V., Sreenivas, R.S., Rogers, W.A. (2021, September)

Presented at the Rehabilitation Engineering and Assistive Technology Society of North America (RESNA) 2021 Virtual Conference.

A Smart Power Outlet for Electric Devices that can Benefit from Real-Time Pricing

V.P. Ramavarapu, R. Sreenivas, R. Sowers

Conference article in The Proceedings of the 2017 International Conference on Control, Electronics, Renewable Energy and Communications (ICCEREC)

Technical Reports

Voice-Activated Digital Home Assistant Application/Skill Development: Instructional Support and Recommendation Application Development for Older Adults with Mobility Disabilities (TechSAge-TR-2108).

V. Ramavarapu, T. Kadylak, W. Rogers (2021).

Rehabilitation Engineering Research Center on Technologies to Support Aging-in-Place for People with Long-Term Disabilities. (Link)

Research Experience

Cyclicity Analysis on COVID19 in North America

Jul. 2021 - May. 2022

Independent Study, University of Illinois at Urbana Champaign

Urbana, II

- · PI: Prof. Yuliy Baryshnikov
- Cyclicity analysis is the technique of aggregating regional linear time series to map spread of a signal over a medium. (Traditionally in neuroscience to map the spread of trauma during a brain injury).
- Using American and Canadian provincial COVID case time series, spread is mapped across North America. Python: Pandas/Matplotlib/Jupyter Notebook
- Conducted a comparative literature review to justify our findings.

Human Factors and Aging Laboratory

Jul. 2020 - May 2022

Undergraduate Research Assistant, University of Illinois at Urbana Champaign

Urbana, IL

- · PI: Prof. Wendy Rogers
- Created Amazon Alexa skills with voice and visual interface using AWS Lambda. Took into account **Nielsens Usability Heuristics** to ensure the app is usable by older adults and those with mobility disabilities. **NodeJS/AWS Lambda**
- Undergraduate Research Symposium 2021: Created a presentation for my independent project under the laboratory. Wrote the abstract for the research project and showcased the development process of the Alexa Application.

A Smart Power Outlet for Electric Devices that can Benefit from Real-Time Pricing

Jun. 2017 - Aug. 2017

Independent Study, University of Illinois at Urbana Champaign

Urbana, IL

- · PIs: Prof. Richard Sowers, Prof. RS Sreenivas
- · Designed algorithms to fetch real-time utility pricing and parse it into a readable format by a programmable Intel Edison.
- Wrote JavaScript Code in Figures 8 and 9 of the above conference paper

TechSAge App Factor: Developing a Novel Voice-Activated Alexa Skill (Awarded: 2021, June)

Funder: TechSAge RERC

Project Title: Amazon Alexa Interactive Help and Recommendation Application for Older Adults with Mobility Disabilities

Team: Travis Kadylak (PI) and Vikram Ramavarapu (Engineering Research Assistant)

Award amount: \$5,000

Professional Experience

Uhnder Inc. Apr. 2022 - Present

Research and Development Intern

Champaign, IL

· Object detection for self driving cars: Trained 2D U-Net on 2D rectangular projections of spherical radar data (r, theta, phi) to perform Semantic Segmentation. Improved mean IoU by 30% since initial segmentation model's implementation. Gitlab, Python: Pytorch/MMSegmentation, AWS S3

· Built methods to validate effectiveness of various self driving car simulator versions: Created methods that used Wasserstein Distance (EMD) to compare simulated and real radar images, as well as older and newer simulator generated images. C++: Catch2/CARLA (Unreal Engine)

HBO Max (Warner Bros. Discovery)

Jan. 2022 - Apr. 2022

Culver City, CA

SWE Intern – Data

- Designed, implemented and productionalized method to identify potential international pricing abusers of the streaming service.
- · Built a scheme to auto-generate the list using an orchestrator Airflow, Snowflake

Exelon Aug. 2021 – Dec. 2021

SWE Co-Op

Inprentus

Chicago, IL

- · Built an application to run statistical analysis of simulations based on the reactor design. Python: Tkinter/Matplotlib/Pandas
- · Reduced analysis time from a week's worth of manual effort to about an hour for over 99% improvement in work efficiency.

Research and Development Intern

Jun. 2018 - May 2019

- Champaign, IL • Built an application to automatically generate precise statistical product reports from Atomic Force Microscopy (AFM) images of diffraction
- gratings. Recipients of these reports included NASA and SLAC (Stanford). Python: Matplotlib/PyGTK
- · Created macros to identify components of Scanning Electron Microscope (SEM) images of indentation tools. ImageJ, Java
- · Material indentation simulations in a joint project with UC Berkeley. Mathematica

Projects

User-Friendly Class Registration System (Demo Video)

Nov. 2021 - Dec. 2021

- Won top 7 in a University Full-Stack contest of roughly 50 teams.
- · User-friendly upgrade to UIUC's class registration system with a REST API in the back-end, and a thoroughly UI-prototyped front-end. Gitlab, JavaScript: React/Express/MongoDB, Miro

VerseNet (Github)

- Designed and trained **Recurrent Neural Network** to generate verses with stylistic similarity to the provided piece of literature. **Python: PyTorch**
- · Neural network has been tested on pieces from Shakespeare to contemporary works.

Certificates

Artificial Intelligence in Medicine

Received Dec. 2021

Carle-Illinois College of Medicine

Urbana, IL

- · Completion of modules on theory (mathematics and statistics) behind the design of CNNs, GANs, RNNs.
- · CNNs for tumor detection, and RNNs to analyze sequences in sleep cycles. PyTorch, Tensorflow

Programming Languages		Technical Skills	
Python:	>100k lines of code	Front End:	React, HTML, CSS, BootStrap
JavaScript:	>50k lines of code	Back End:	Django, Node.js, Express.js
C/C++:	>50k lines of code	Databases:	SQL, MongoDB, Neo4j
Java:	>10k lines of code	Machine Learning:	PyTorch, Tensorflow, OpenCV
Shell:	>500 lines of code	AWS:	S3, EC2, Lambda